{"tossups": [{"question": "This man advocated for a \u201cpriesthood of all believers\u201d in the work<em> To the Christian Nobility of the</em> <em>German Nation</em>. He was protected by Frederick the Wise after Charles V ordered his arrest. Pope Leo X excommunicated this man with the bull<em> Exsurge Domine</em> [EX-ur-gay DOE-mee-nay] after he posted the 95 Theses. For ten points, name this German priest who began the Protestant Reformation.", "answer": "Martin<b> Luther</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This nation was invaded by Huang Taiji in 1636 as the Qing [CHING] dynasty sought to solidify its war against the Ming. In 1592, Toyotomi Hideyoshi\u2019s invasion of this nation was disrupted by enemy turtle ships. The Joseon dynasty ruled it until 1897, and it was annexed by Japan in 1910. For ten points, name this East Asian peninsula split after World War II by Soviet and American agreement into two countries with capitals Pyongyang and Seoul.", "answer": "<b> Korea</b>n Peninsula (accept Joseon Kingdom, Dynasty, or similar before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Shoshone [sho-sho-nay] Falls and Twin Falls lie on this river, whose largest tributary is the Salmon River. In 1974, Evel Knievel\u2019s Skycycle X-2 nearly jumped a canyon of this tributary of the Columbia River. For ten points, name this river that flows through Hells Canyon after receiving the Boise River near the border of Oregon and Idaho.", "answer": "<b> Snake</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The rVSV-ZEBOV vaccine has been shown effective in treating this disease. Emile Ouamouno died six days after contracting this disease, and Eric Duncan infected two Americans with it. Liberia was declared free of this disease after 42 days with no new cases. For ten points, name this disease which caused a 2014 epidemic in West Africa.", "answer": "<b> Ebola</b> virus disease (or<b> Ebola</b> hemorrhagic fever)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "In the Hellenistic period, this deity was syncretized with Apis to form the god Serapis. The djed pillar represented the spine of this deity, whose wife searched throughout Egypt to find the 14 pieces of his body after he was torn apart by his jealous brother, Set. For ten points, name this Egyptian god of the afterlife whose consort was his sister, Isis.", "answer": "<b> Osiris</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "Neil Armstrong took a recording of theramin music and this man\u2019s ninth symphony on Apollo 11. He wrote his twelfth string quartet while spending a summer in Spillville, Iowa, though his<em> Slavonic Dances</em> honored Brahms and paid tribute to his native Bohemia. For ten points, name this Czech composer who, while visiting America, wrote his Symphony no. 9, \u201cFrom the New World.\u201d", "answer": "Antonin<b> Dvorak</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "One artist from this country classified his work as \u201cstabiles\u201d and \u201cmobiles,\u201d one of which consists of aluminum fins suspended on steel wire. That artist from this country, Alexander Calder, also created<em> Bent</em> <em>Propeller</em>, which was destroyed when the Minoru Yamasaki-designed World Trade Center was attacked on 9/11. For ten points, name this country, home of the Museum of Modern Art in New York.", "answer": "United States of<b> America</b> (accept<b> US</b>A or clear equivalents)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Supporters of this party were victims of the White Terror Massacre. The Xian [SHEE-ahn] incident was perpetrated by members of this party. The Gang of Four consisted of members of this party and were later found guilty of treason near the end of one of this party\u2019s efforts, the Cultural Revolution. For ten points, name this ruling party of an Asian nation once led by Mao Zedong.", "answer": "<b> Communist</b> Party of<b> China</b> (or<b> Chinese Communist</b> Party; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This organization founded the Bowen Country Club as a summer camp. Toynbee Hall inspired this institution, which was founded on Halsted Street by Ellen Gates Starr and the first American woman to win a Nobel Peace Prize. This organization started providing education and support to the poor in 1889. For ten points, name this settlement house in Chicago co-founded by Jane Addams.", "answer": "<b> Hull House</b> <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country featured the highest scorer at the inaugural FIFA World Cup, Guillermo Stabile, whose team lost to Uruguay in the finals. Mario Kempes led this country to a 1978 World Cup win as the host nation. In this country\u2019s win over England at the 1986 World Cup, the \u201cHand of God\u201d scored one goal for Diego Maradona. For ten points, name this country whose soccer team, led by Lionel Messi, placed second in the 2014 World Cup.", "answer": "<b> Argentina</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "Nicholas Reeves has controversially suggested using radar in this location to find hidden rooms. Pierre Lacau supervised a study of this location funded by Lord Carnavon who died of mosquito-borne disease shortly after it was opened. This location, officially designated KV62, was discovered in 1922 by Howard Carter. For ten points, name this surprisingly well-preserved burial site of a boy pharaoh.", "answer": "the<b> tomb</b> of King<b> Tut</b>ankhamun (accept<b> KV62</b> before mentioned; accept equivalents for tomb, such as<b> crypt</b> or<b> burial site</b>, before mentioned; do not accept anything related to pyramids)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "When asked about violence against followers of this religion, one politician responded, \u201cWhen a big tree falls, the earth shakes.\u201d An empire named for this religion ruled the Punjab under Maharaja Ranjit Singh during the first half of the 19th century. For ten points, name this monotheistic religion founded by Guru Nanak whose male adherents follow five articles of faith, including the keeping of uncut hair.", "answer": "<b> Sikh</b>ism", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This country owns, but is not allowed to navigate, the western wetlands surrounding Lago Merin at the delta of the Yaguaron River. Its western border is a river named for this country; that river combines with the Parana River to form the Rio de la Plata. For ten points, name this country southwest of Brazil whose capital is Montevideo.", "answer": "<b> Uruguay</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Tral stations and the Command-Measurement Complex were used to observe this object. A part of this vehicle was derived from an R7 intercontinental ballistic missile, and it used</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>four radio antennas to broadcast a repeating, pulsing signal. President Eisenhower</b> <b>created ARPA and the government increased funding for (*)</b> science and technology after this object was launched in October 1957. The Soviets started the Space Race with the launch of, for ten points, what first artificial satellite?", "answer": "<b> Sputnik</b> I (prompt on Satellite 1)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this conservative commentator whose talk-radio show is the most-listened-to radio program in the United States.", "answer": "Rush<b> Limbaugh</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "</b> <b>Another mayor of this city drew criticism for limiting the size of (+) sugary soft drinks and</b> <b>for his stop-and-frisk policy, the latter of which (*)</b> Bill de Blasio campaigned against in 2013. Michael Bloomberg was a three-term mayor of, for ten points, what American city in which the police patrol Central Park and Times Square?", "answer": "<b> New York</b> City (or<b> NYC</b>) Page 8", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In this state, one state senator filibustered this state\u2019s Senate Bill 5, which would have limited access to abortions. That senator, Wendy Davis, lost in the 2014 gubernatorial</b> <b>elections for this state. The (+)</b> <b>presidential campaign of one Senator from this state</b> <b>aroused controversy, as he was born in Canada; that senator is the first (*)</b> Cuban-American to run for the presidency, Ted Cruz. For ten points, name this state whose current Governor, Greg Abbott, succeeded the longest-serving governor in state history, Rick Perry.", "answer": "<b> Texas</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>This man renounced his original citizenship in 1985 to legally become the owner of an American TV station. He lured Sam Chisholm away from Kerry Packer\u2019s Nine Network to</b> <b>be the CEO of his company, (+)</b> <b>British Sky Broadcasting, and his conglomerate acquired</b> <b>the</b><em><b> Wall Street Journal</b></em><b> in 2007. His tabloid, (*)</b><em> News of the World</em>, was shuttered in 2011 after a celebrity phone hacking scandal. For ten points, name this founder of News Corp who, in 2015, stepped down as CEO of 21st Century Fox.", "answer": "Rupert<b> Murdoch</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>This man destroyed the Vandals after his generals won the battles of Tricamerum and Ad Decimum. The</b><em><b> Secret History</b></em><b> by Procopius detailed the rule of this emperor and his</b> <b>marriage to a (+)</b> <b>courtesan who convinced him to stay after a riot by the Blues and</b> <b>Greens. This survivor of the Nika Riots formed the (*)</b><em> Corpus Juris Civilis</em>, later known as his namesake \u201cCode.\u201d For ten points, name this Byzantine emperor who built the Hagia Sophia.", "answer": "<b> Justinian</b> the<b> Great</b> (or<b> Justinian I</b>; prompt on Justinian) ", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}